Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union PE.013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
1903-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.013
7 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons and 3 shared boxes
The Printed Ephemera Collection on the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) (1903-2009) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The ILGWU, founded in 1900, led the fight to organize workers in the garment trades, greatly improving the lives and the working conditions for hundreds of thousands of clothing workers in the United States. The collection is a rich source of history of the ILGWU, as told through their numerous and wonderfully illustrated story books and pamphlets. The collection also contains a range of printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, reprinted articles, manuals and other publications. Material in the collection comes from various departments of the international and national bodies of the ILGWU. Workers education was a primary concern to the ILGWU, and thus a sizable portion of the collection comes from their Education Department. Additionally, this collection provides material from locals, regions, and Joint Boards from around the country, but most notably from New York City, arguably the center of activity for the ILGWU, and includes material from New York City locals 1, 10, 22, and 91 among others.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Historical Note
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) was founded in New York City in 1900 in an effort to consolidate the power of the various garment trades into one collective force. The history of garment workers in general and of the nascent organizing efforts of the ILGWU in the early 20th century is plagued with tragedy, most well-known being the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire of 1911 that claimed the lives of 146 workers who were locked into the factory and could not escape when a fire broke out. However, despite difficult conditions the ILGWU was hugely successful through work stoppages and strike campaigns in organizing large masses of garment workers in New York and around the country, establishing better working conditions and shorter working hours. In 1909, shirtwaist workers revolted in what was known as the "Uprising of 20,000" that eventually won the 52-hour work week. Over the next decade, strikes all over the country continued to win better conditions for garment workers. In 1913, the Union Health Center was established in New York City and provided decent and urgently needed health care for union members. Due to internal strife involving communist and anti-communist leadership, hardening economic conditions as well as anti-union efforts, the ILGWU and its membership suffered through the 1920s. Roosevelt's presidency and better labor laws brought a resurgence to organizing. David Dubinsky became president of the union in 1932 and served until 1966. Under Dubinsky's leadership, the union helped establish the Congress of Industrial Organizations, but eventually disaffiliated with them and went back to the American Federation of Labor in 1940. The ILGWU was a trailblazer in terms of providing education for workers, The Union's Education Department was vibrant, churning out pamphlets and publication on union history, membership and leadership. The ILGWU established social centers, offering numerous educational, community and athletic activities for its membership. Communism and corruption continued to be major sources of internal struggle for the ILGWU through the 1950s.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). Then in 2004, UNITE and the Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union (HERE) merged to form Unite Here.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (IGWLU) (1903-2009) provides a rich source of information on the ILGWU's organizing activities, education campaigns and internal struggles. Comprised of constitutions and reports, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications, the collection ranges in date from 1903-2009.
Providing workers with access to education was a key effort of the ILGWU. Consequently, their Education Department was prolific in churning out manuals, guides, and histories on the Union. Cultural activities were also an important aspect of building the Union, and the ILGWU established social centers, providing members with classes and lectures as well athletic and social events. Premiering in Hollywood in 1950, the ILGWU presented a movie about their history, "With these Hands," and the collection contains fliers, promotional material, and pamphlets about the film.
Bernard Seaman, a talented illustrator, drew the artwork for a considerable number of pamphlets and publications in the collection. His work is striking and lends the printed material of the ILGWU its unique aesthetic.
The ILGWU was founded in New York City, though its membership grew and spread throughout the country. The material in this collection comes largely from the national and international bodies, but also the locals, regionals, and Joint Boards in and around New York City. Most notably are the Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union (Local 10), the Dressmakers Union (Local 22), the Northeast Department and the Joint Board of Dress and Waistmakers' Union of Greater New York.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. The accession number NPA.2000.272 is associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Pamphlets.; Publications (documents); Fliers (printed matter); Agreements.; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Printed ephemera.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Organizing.; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions -- New York (N.Y.); Labor unions; Labor unions -- United States.; Constitutions.; Clippings (information artifacts); Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Educational Department
- Anniversaries and Commemorations, 1957-1960, 1970-1975, 1994, 2009 (Box 1)
- Archives, 1980-1982, undated (Box 1)
- Athletic League, 1935 (Box 1)
- Auditing Department, 1941-1968 (Box 1)
- Baltimore Joint Board, circa 1945 (Box 1)
- Business Agents, 1962-1963, undated (Box 1)
- Campaign for Justice, 1990 (Box 1)
- Central and Western Pennsylvania District, undated (Box 1)
- Chicago Joint Board, 1934, undated (Box 1)
- Circular and Open Letters, 1937-1965, 1987, 1995, undated (Box 1)
- Cleveland Joint Board, 1932-1934 (Box 1)
- Cloak Out-of-Town Department, 1950, 1960, undated (Box 1)
- Constitutional Conventions, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 005, Folder 11)
- Constitutional Conventions, 1940 (Box 1)
- Constitutional Conventions, 1944-1959 (Box 1)
- Constitutional Conventions, 1962 (Box 1)
- Constitutional Conventions: Educational Dept. Reports, 1928-1959 (Box 1)
- Constitutional Conventions: Financial and Statistical Reports, 1934-1965 (Box 1)
- Constitutional Conventions: "Trends and Prospects in the Women's Garment Industry", 1940-1959 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1934-1956 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1962-1986 (Box 1)
- Consumer Service Division, 1976, undated (Box 1)
- Cotton Dress and Miscellaneous Trades Department, 1937 (Box 1)
- Cotton Garment and Miscellaneous Trades Department, 1946 (Box 1)
- Cultural Division (Including Art Exhibits, Concerts, Pageants and Plays), 1940-1958 (Box 1)
- Death Benefit Fund, 1937, 1953-1956 (Box 1)
- Dress and Waist Manufacturers' Association, 1913 (Box 1)
- Dressmakers' General Strike, 1958, undated (Box 1)
- Dubinsky, David, 1942 (Box 1)
- Dubrow, Evelyn, 1992 (Box 1)
- Eastern Out-of-Town Department, 1950-1956, undated (Box 1)
- Eastern Region, undated (Box 1)
- Educational Department: Announcement and Schedule of Courses Given in Workers' Education, 1921-1926 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Bulletins and Newsletters, 1927, 1955-1957 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Central Classes, 1950-1960, undated (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Circular Letters, 1935-1936, undated (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Educational Programs, 1937-1948 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Film Strips, 1958, undated (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Fliers, 1937-1942, 1950, undated (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Lecture Series, 1937-1938, undated (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Officers Qualification Courses, 1939, 1959 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1922, 1930-1934 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1938 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1939-1940 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1941 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1943-1946 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1947-1949 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Panel Discussions, 1942-1955 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Plays, 1936, 1941, undated (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Press Releases, circa 1951 (Box 2)
- Educational Department: Publications, Compilation of, 1942-1945, undated (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Publications, Brochures and Lists of, 1939-1942, undated (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Reports, 1924-1959 (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Reprints, 1926-1959, undated (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Songs and Poems, 1927-1959, undated (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Study Outlines for Teachers, 1924-1935, undated (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Study Outlines for Teachers, 1936 (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Training-for-Trade-Union-Service Courses, 1933-1938, undated (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Training-for-Trade-Union-Service Courses, 1940-1959 (Box 3)
- Educational Department: Training-for-Trade-Union-Service Publications, 1935-1942, undated (Box 3)
- Elections (New York), circa 1940s (Box 3)
- Elections (U.S. Presidential), 1944, 1960, 1968 (Box 3)
- Federation of Union Representatives (FOUR), 1963 (Box 3)
- Films, 1950, undated (Box 3)
- Fliers and Ephemera, 1937-1947, undated (Box 3)
- Fliers and Ephemera, circa 1960s-1995, undated (Box 3)
- Health and Safety Department, undated (Box 3)
- Hearings and Trials, 1939, 1957, undated (Box 3)
- History, circa 1940s-circa 1960s, undated (Box 3)
- Houses, Inc., 1960 (Box 3)
- Industrial Council of Cloak, Suit and Skirt Manufacturers, Inc., 1935 (Box 3)
- International Affairs, 1950, undated (Box 3)
- Joint Board Cloak, Skirt, Dress and Reefer Makers' Unions, 1927 (Box 3)
- Joint Board Cloak, Suit and Dressmakers' Unions, undated (Box 3)
- Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt and Reefer Makers' Unions, 1927-1948, undated (Box 3)
- Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt and Reefer Makers' Unions, 1950-1970 (Box 3)
- Joint Board of Cloak, Suit, Skirt and Reefer Makers' Unions: Health, Welfare and Retirement Funds, 1943-1970 (Box 3)
- Joint Board of Dress and Waistmakers Union of Greater New York, 1936-1965, undated (Box 4)
- Joint Board of Dress and Waistmakers Union of Greater New York: Agreements, 1938-1944 (Box 4)
- Joint Board of Dress and Waistmakers Union of Greater New York: Agreements, 1955-1973 (Box 4)
- Justice: Reprints, Special Editions and Souvenir Copies, 1944-1962, 1971 (Box 4, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 16)
- Legal Department, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
- Levy, Louis, 1943 (Box 4)
- Local 1 (New York, NY) (I), 1936 (Box 4)
- Local 1 (New York, NY) (II), 1936 (Box 4)
- Local 10 (Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union, New York, NY), 1936-1968, undated (Box 4, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 14)
- Local 10 (Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union, New York, NY), 1936 (Box 4)
- Local 10 (Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union, New York, NY): Anniversaries, 1952-1972 (Box 4)
- Local 20 (Waterproof Garment Workers Union, New York, NY), 1968 (Box 4)
- Local 22 (Dressmakers Union, New York, NY), undated (Box 4)
- Local 22 (Dressmakers Union, New York, NY), 1934 (Box 4)
- Local 22 (Dressmakers Union, New York, NY), 1935-1937 (Box 4)
- Local 22 (Dressmakers Union, New York, NY), 1938-1939 (Box 4)
- Local 22 (Dressmakers Union, New York, NY), 1940-1948 (Box 4)
- Local 22 (Dressmakers Union, New York, NY), 1950-1965 (Box 4)
- Local 23 (Skirtmakers Union, New York, NY), 1938-1956, undated (Box 4)
- Local 23-25 (Blouse, Skirt and Sportswear Workers Union, New York, NY), 1971-1984, undated (Box 4, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 15)
- Local 32 (Corset and Brassiere Workers Union, New York, NY), 1954 (Box 4)
- Local 35 (Cloak and Skirt Pressers Union, New York, NY), 1944 (Box 4)
- Local 38 (Ladies Tailors, Custom Dressmakers and Alteration Workers, New York, NY), 1940, undated (Box 4)
- Local 40 (Beltmakers' Union, New York, NY), 1949, undated (Box 4)
- Local 44 (Los Angeles, CA), 1989 (Box 4)
- Local 48 (Italian Cloak, Suit, Skirt and Reefer Makers' Union, New York, NY), 1937, undated (Box 4)
- Local 50 (Waist and Dressmakers Union, Philadelphia, PA), undated (Box 4)
- Local 60 (Dress and Waist Pressers Union, New York, NY), undated (Box 4)
- Local 62 (Undergarment and Negligee Workers Union, New York, NY), 1938-1959 (Box 5)
- Local 66 (Bonnaz, Embroideries, Tacking, Pleating and Allied Crafts Union, New York, NY), 1937-1973 (Box 5)
- Local 85, 1956 (Box 5)
- Local 89 (Italian Press and Waistmakers Union, New York, NY), 1935-1944, undated (Box 5)
- Local 91 (New York, NY), 1937-1943, undated (Box 5)
- Local 91 (New York, NY), 1946-1963, 1985 (Box 5)
- Local 99, 1959 (Box 5)
- Local 105 (New York, NY), 1951-1961, undated (Box 5)
- Local 107, undated (Box 5)
- Local 108 (Harrisburg, PA), undated (Box 5)
- Local 111 (Allentown, PA), 1953 (Box 5)
- Local 117 (New York, NY), 1953-1961, undated (Box 5)
- Local 132 (Plastic Moulders and Novelty Workers Union), 1957 (Box 5)
- Local 134, 1952 (Box 5)
- Local 142, 1953, 1959 (Box 5)
- Local 143 (Westchester, NY), undated (Box 5)
- Local 155 (Knitgoods Workers Union, New York, NY), 1944-1972, undated (Box 5)
- Local 190 (Knitgoods Workers Union, Philadelphia, PA), 1959 (Box 5)
- Local 262 (Montreal Dressmakers Union), 1952 (Box 5)
- Local 365 (Sayre, PA), undated (Box 5)
- Local 454 (Goshen, IN), 1946 (Box 5)
- Local 482, undated (Box 5)
- Local 600 (Puerto Rico), 1973 (Box 5)
- Locaux 205-262 (Union Internationale des Ouvriers du Vêtement pour Dames), 1964 (Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 17)
- Los Angeles Dress and Sportswear Joint Board, 1957 (Box 5)
- Los Angeles Dress and Sportswear Joint Board: Leadership Training Institute (1957) (I), 1955-1957, undated (Box 5)
- Los Angeles Dress and Sportswear Joint Board: Leadership Training Institute (1957) (II), 1955-1957, undated (Box 5)
- Midwest Department, 1957 (Box 5)
- National Industrial Recovery Act: Proposed Codes, 1933 (Box 5)
- New York General Strike, 1934 (Box 5)
- Newsletters, 1948 (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles on, 1935-1993, undated (Box 5)
- Northeast Department, undated (Box 5)
- Northeast Department, 1950-1956 (Box 5)
- Northeast Department, 1958-1965 (Box 5)
- Northeast Department: Union Training, 1956-1957, undated (Box 5)
- Pacific Coast Education, 1942 (Box 6)
- Pamphlets and Publications (General ILGWU), 1903, 1938-1947, undated (Box 6)
- Pamphlets and Publications (General ILGWU), 1950-1953 (Box 6)
- Pamphlets and Publications (General ILGWU), 1954-1980 (Box 6)
- Philadelphia Joint Board (Philadelphia, PA), 1939-1957, undated (Box 6)
- Philadelphia Joint Board (Philadelphia, PA): Leadership Training Institute, 1957 (Box 6)
- Political Department, undated (Box 6)
- Political Institute, 1951 (Box 6)
- Press Releases, 1946-1966, undated (Box 6)
- Public Service Publications: "Legislative Representation in New York State", 1957-1963 (Box 6)
- Rank and File, 1962, 1972, undated (Box 6)
- Research Department, 1952, 1958 (Box 6)
- Research Department, 1963, 1994 (Box 6)
- Research Reports, 1939, undated (Box 6)
- Research Reports, 1941 (Box 6)
- Rosters, 1943, 1946, 1981 (Box 6)
- Speeches and Interviews, 1941-1959 (Box 6)
- Songbooks, 1935-1975, undated (Box 6)
- Southeastern Regional Office, undated (Box 6)
- South Bronx Working Center, undated (Box 6)
- Southwestern Regional Office, 1942, undated (Box 6)
- Student Fellowship: Annual Reunion, 1941 (Box 6)
- Suggested Provisions for Agreements, undated (Box 6)
- Training Institute, undated (Box 6)
- Training Institute: "Sample Book of Leaflets", 1958 (Box 6)
- Union Health Center, 1931-1934 (Box 6)
- Union Health Center, 1931-1964 (Box 6)
- Union Label Department, 1959-1973, undated (Box 6)
- Unity House, 1928, 1990 (Box 6)
- Welfare and Health Benefits Department, 1951-1973, undated (Box 6)
- Worker-Family Education Program, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
- ILGWU Local 105 charter, 1941 (Box Shared Tamiment 016, Folder 1)